The Audio Listener component is the equivalent
Audio Listener コンポーネントはゲームにおける
of your ears in the game.
耳にあたります。
It receives, or listens, to audio sources
ゲーム世界にある音源から音を入力する、
that are in the game world.
つまり音を聞く（Listen) 役割です。
The control of the audio's behaviour is done on
オーディオの動作制御は
the audio source component
Audio Source コンポーネントで行われるため
and therefore the listener itself has no settings.
Listener そのものには設定がありません。
This is attached to a camera in your scene by default
これはシーン中のカメラにアタッチされますが、
but can be placed on any object.
どのようなオブジェクトにもつけることが出来ます。
Often this is attached to a character
キャラクターにアタッチされていることが多く、
and crucially there can be only one listener
シーンごとにひとつだけ Listener を配置することは
per scene in order for it to function correctly.
機能が正しく動作するうえで重要です。
You can test an audio listener from any position in the world
ワールド空間の任意の位置からでも Audio Listener を試すには
by moving the scene camera around
シーンのカメラを動きまわして
with the audio preview toggle enabled.
このオーディオ プレビュー のボタンが有効になっている必要があります。
This gives you live testing of audio sources
これにより環境にある Audio Source のライブテストが可能であり
in your environment without having to move
実際の Listener を動かしたり
the real listener or play test the game.
ゲームで Play ボタンを押す必要がありません。
Audio sources are components that playback audio.
Audio Soruce は音声を再生するコンポーネントです。
Think of them as speakers in the game world.
ゲーム世界におけるスピーカーのようなものです。
In this example our turbine has an audio source attached
このサンプルではタービンには Audio Source がアタッチされていて
with the turbine audio clip that's been applied to it.
タービン用のオーディオクリップが適用されています。
We can assign a clip by dragging and dropping,
オーディオクリップを割り当てるにはドラッグ＆ドロップをするか、
or by using code to select a clip to play.
コードにより再生するオーディオクリップを選択できます。
We can mute, bypass any filters,
ミュートしたり、フィルタをバイパスしたり、
choose whether to play this audio source on awake,
On Awake、すなわちゲームの開始時に
as in - when the game begins
この Audio Source を再生したり、
and whether to loop the clip.
オーディオクリップをループ再生したりします。
Priority varies between 0 and 255,
優先度 (Priority) は 0 から 255 の範囲で変動し、
0 being the highest priority.
0 が最大の優先度です。
It's advisable to have music set as the highest priority
ゲーム ミュージックに最大の優先度をセットすることを推奨します。
to avoid other clips from overriding
これによって、多くのオーディオクリップがが同時再生されたときに
when many clips are being played at once.
他のオーディオクリップにより、ミュージックが再生されないことを回避します。
Volume determines how loud the clip is played
Volume はオーディオクリップの音量を
based on it's original waveform.
オリジナルの音声波形に応じて決定します。
Pitch controls the pitch of a clip.
Pitch はオーディオクリップのピッチを制御します。
If you're working with 3D sounds
3D 音源で作業をしている場合は
the settings are more detailed.
より詳細な設定があります。
Doppler level defines how much the Doppler Effect
Dopper Level により ドップラー効果を
will be used.
どの程度使用するか定義します。
This is a perceived shift in frequency as the listener
これは音の聞き手や
or the ear in real terms
実際人のの耳が音源を通り過ぎるときに
is moving past the sound source.
周波数がシフトすると感じる現象です。
It will seem higher approaching it
これは近づく時に高い周波数と感じ、
and lower as it moves away.
遠ざかるにつれ低く感じます。
Think of an emergency vehicle's siren as it passes you
例えば、救急車のサイレンが自分の側を通り過ぎたときを
for example.
思い浮かべてください。
Volume roll-off determines the type of roll-off
Volume roll-off により、Listener が遠ざかるときに
to be used by the sound
音により使用される
as the listener moves away from it.
減衰の仕方を決定します。
This can be logarithmic, linear,
これは 対数、線形、または
or customised manually using a curve
カーブを手動でカスタマイズして
and adding keys as shown.
表示されているようにキーを追加することができます。
The minimum distance defines how close
Minimum Distance は最大音量で音を再生するときの
to play the sound at full volume.
距離の最小値を定義します。
So if you are designing 3D sound
このため 3D 音声を設計するとき
use this value to make the sound source louder.
この値を使用して音源を大きくします。
This can be adjusted using the spherical Gizmo
これはシーンビューにおける
in the scene view.
球の形の Gizmo を使用して調整できます。
And it works in the conjunction with the
そしてこれは
maximum distance setting below,
以下の Maximum Distance 設定と連動して
which by default is set to 500 metres
デフォルトでは 500 メートルに設定されていて
and is a distance after which
音声が完全に消失するときの
the sound rolls off.
距離です。
Pan level defines how truly 3D the sound is.
Pan level により、音声を純正な 3D とする程度を定義します。
This defaults to 1 for 3D sound
デフォルトでは 1 であるため、3D 音声として
making it fully panned when the stereo listener
ステレオ リスナーが通り過ぎたときに
is moved past it.
完全に Pan します。
Spread is the control of the angle of spread
Spread とは、 3D 音声がマルチチャネルサウンドへの
from 3D stereo to multichannel sound.
広がりの角度をコントロールします。
Finally for 2D sound pan can be controlled
最後に 2D Sound Pan はコンポーネントの最下部で
at the bottom of the component.
制御できます。
As a rule elements such as music
原則としてゲームミュージックのような要素は
should be set to 2D sound,
は2D 音声にセットとすべきです。
whilst diegetic sound that should be
一方で、物語世界の音（Diegetic Sound）で
fading realistically should be set up
フェードするのがリアリティを高める場合は
as 3D and positioned accordingly.
3D 音声にセットして位置を適切にすべきです。
The 2D and 3D values of a sound
音の 2D および 3D の値は
are controlled by an audio clip's import settings.
オーディオクリップの Import Settings で制御できます。
When selecting a clip in the project
プロジェクトでオーディオクリップを選択するとき
you will be able to see the import settings
インスペクタ上で Import Settings
in the inspector.
をみることが出来ます。
You can choose the audio format to use,
使用するオーディオ フォーマットは選択するこが出来ます。
whether it should be 3D or 2D sound,
3D 音声なのか、 2D 音声なのか、
whether you want to force your stereo sound to mono,
あるいはステレオ音声をモノラル音声に強制的に変更するか
how to load it and what compression to use.
どのようにロードして、どのような圧縮を使用するか、など決定します。
You can also preview sound at the bottom,
音声は最下部でプレビューすることが出来て、
choose whether to loop whilst previewing
プレビューの際にループするか選択をして、
and set the inspector to auto-play
そしてオーディオクリップをブラウズする際に
whilst browsing through clips.
インスペクタ上で自動再生するかセットできます。 (翻訳:gamesonytablet)